<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alexis Duque</title>
    <description>Director of Research @Rtone&lt;br&gt;Ph.D. #iot #ml #vlc #security 💡🔑🚴‍</description>
    <link>http://alexisduque.me/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://alexisduque.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 21:00:57 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 21:00:57 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.3.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Webinar on mobile traffic decomposition using Deep Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On November 16th, I will give a webinar part of ITU AI for Good serie on  &lt;a href=&quot;https://aiforgood.itu.int/events/harnessing-deep-learning-for-mobile-service-traffic-decomposition-to-support-network-slicing/&quot;&gt;Harnessing Deep Learning for Mobile Service Traffic Decomposition to Support Network Slicing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Network slicing enables operators to isolate and customize mobile network resources on a per-service basis. Provisioning resources to slices requires real-time information about the traffic demands generated by individual services, which is challenging to acquire. This talk will first present an original deep learning approach to service-level demand estimation that relies only on total traffic aggregates. Experimental results with metropolitan-scale network measurements will reveal that the proposed solution infers per-service traffic demands with 99% accuracy. The talk will then introduce a dynamic convolution operator that resolves the grid-structural data requirements of existing spatiotemporal inference models recently proposed for mobile traffic analysis. Further, it will be shown that this operator can be easily plugged into traditional LSTM architectures to deliver accurate long-term traffic predictions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 09:36:31 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2020/10/04/itu/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2020/10/04/itu/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Paper accepted at MLCS'20</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The paper “MitM Attack Detection in BLE Networks using Reconstruction and Classification Machine Learning Techniques”, co-authored with Abdelkader Lahmadi, Nathan Heraief and Julien Francq, has been accepted for publication in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mlcs.lasige.di.fc.ul.pt/&quot;&gt;Machine Learning for Cybersecurity Workshop&lt;/a&gt; to be held virtually on September 14th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full paper has been included in the conference proceedings that can be accessed &lt;a href=&quot;/public/ml-ble-mlcs2020-CR.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentation slides are available &lt;a href=&quot;/public/slides_ML-BLE.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 09:36:31 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2020/09/01/mlcs-2020/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2020/09/01/mlcs-2020/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Elsevier Computer Communications Journal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The paper “Analytical and simulation tools for optical camera communications”, co-authored with Razvan Stanica, Hervé Rivano and Adrien Desportes, has been accepted for publication in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0140366420310896&quot;&gt;Elsevier Computer Communication&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 09:36:31 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2020/07/01/comcom/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2020/07/01/comcom/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ACM MSWiM full paper</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The paper “Performance Evaluation of LED-to-Camera Communication”, co-authored with Razvan Stanica, Hervé Rivano and Adrien Desportes, has been accepted for publication at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mswimconf.com/2019/&quot;&gt;ACM MSWiM&lt;/a&gt;, to be held in Miami Beach, Florida, USA on November 25-29.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the conference, I introduced our work on the modeling and simulation of LED-to-Camera communications by presenting &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vlc-citi-lab/camcomsim&quot;&gt;CamComSim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full paper has been included in the conference proceedings that can be accessed &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3355922&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My presentation slides are available below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;b62f0dee83154609935b0af99764d188&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.33333333333333&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 08:36:31 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2019/11/25/mswim-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2019/11/25/mswim-2019/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Devoxx 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From November 03 to 14, I attended the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.devoxx.be&quot;&gt;Devoxx BE&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.devoxx.ma&quot;&gt;Devoxx Morocco&lt;/a&gt; conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During these software developer events, I gave a Tool-in-Action talks about &lt;a href=&quot;https://devoxx.be/talk/?id=37401&quot;&gt;Machine Learning on IoT and Tensorflow Lite&lt;/a&gt; and a lightening talk introducing &lt;a href=&quot;https://devoxx.be/wednesday-schedule/talk?id=38051&quot;&gt;5G&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can watch the recording of both talk on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCCBVCTuk6uJrN3iFV_3vurg&quot;&gt;Devoxx YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;4a9fb4ad2c014fa09dd685546a9c5f73&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.77777777777778&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;5e98ea67d45d4240bae4a0d572e06d43&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.77777777777778&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 08:44:34 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2019/11/03/devoxx-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2019/11/03/devoxx-2019/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Linux Foundation Open Source Summit 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;From October 28 to 31, I attended the &lt;a href=&quot;https://events19.linuxfoundation.org/events/open-source-summit-europe-2019/&quot;&gt;Linux Foundation Open Source Summit and Embedded Linux Conference Europe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this software developer events, I gave a quick talk about &lt;a href=&quot;https://paclido.fr/lilliput-ae/&quot;&gt;Lilliput-AE&lt;/a&gt;, a lightweight cryptographic block cipher that is a result of the collaborative research project &lt;a href=&quot;https://paclido.fr&quot;&gt;PACLIDO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;463e6c4123614d2dad936154173c462d&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.77777777777778&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 08:44:34 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2019/11/03/lfelc-2019/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2019/11/03/lfelc-2019/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD Defense Presentation Slides</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Slides of my PhD defense “Bidirectional Visible Light Communications for the Internet of Things” are available here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/alexisduque/phd-defense-bidirectional-visible-light-communications-for-the-internet-of-things&quot;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will share the manuscript very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;767bd8b707aa4501aa269bebb122459b&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.33333333333333&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 18:44:34 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2018/10/11/defense-slides/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2018/10/11/defense-slides/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD Defense on Monday 9th October</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After 3 year of intensive at &lt;strong&gt;Rtone&lt;/strong&gt; and in the &lt;strong&gt;AGORA&lt;/strong&gt; of the &lt;strong&gt;CITI Lab&lt;/strong&gt;, I’m proud to announce that I will defend  my PhD thesis &lt;em&gt;“Bidirectional Visible Light Communications for the Internet of Things”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will take place on &lt;strong&gt;Tuesday October 9th&lt;/strong&gt; starting at 2PM, at the &lt;em&gt;Amphitheater CHAPPE - Department TC, INSA de Lyon, 6 avenue des arts, Villeurbanne&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find an abstract of the thesis and the jury in the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-jury-will-be-composed-of&quot;&gt;The jury will be composed of:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emmanuel CHAPUT&lt;/strong&gt;, Professeur des Universités, INP Toulouse, Rapporteur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anne JULIEN-VERGONJANNE&lt;/strong&gt;, Professeur des Universités Univ. Limoges, Rapporteur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Josep PARADELLS ASPAS&lt;/strong&gt;, Professeur UPC, Rapporteur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Luc CHASSAGNE&lt;/strong&gt;, Professeur des Universités UVSQ, Examinateur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Valeria LOSCRI&lt;/strong&gt;, Chargé de Recherche INRIA Lille, Examinateur&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hervé RIVANO&lt;/strong&gt;, Professeur des Universités INSA Lyon, Directeur de thèse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Razvan STANICA&lt;/strong&gt;, Maître de Conférences INSA Lyon, co Directeur de thèse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exponential growth of the Internet of Things, people now expect every household appliance to be smart and connected. At the same time, smartphones have become ubiquitous in our daily life. Their continuous performance improvement and their compatibility with a broad range of radio protocols as WiFi, Bluetooth Low Energy (BLE) or NFC make them the most convenient way to interact with these smart objects. However, providing wireless connectivity with BLE or NFC means adding an extra chipset and an antenna, increasing the object size and price. Previous works already have demonstrated the possibility of receiving information through visible light using an unmodified smartphone thanks to its camera. Also, LED-to-LED communication for smart devices like toys has been shown previously. However, past efforts in LED to camera communication for IoT device communication have been limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this work, we design LightIoT, a bidirectional visible-light communication (VLC) system between a low-cost, low-power colored LED that is part of an IoT device and an off-the-shelf smartphone. The IoT device is thus able to send and receive information through its LED, while the smartphone uses its camera to receive data and its flashlight to send information. We implement and experimentally evaluate a LED-to-camera VLC system, designed specifically for small LEDs. The proposed solution exploits the rolling shutter effect of unmodified smartphone cameras and an original decoding algorithm, achieving a throughput of nearly 2 kb/s.
Based on the insight gained from an extensive experimental study, we model, for the first time in the literature, the LED-to-camera communication channel. We propose a Markov-modulated Bernoulli process model, which allows us to easily study the performance of different message retransmission strategies. We further exploit this model to implement a simulator for LED-to- Camera communications performance evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to achieve bi-directional communications, we evaluate flashlight-to- LED communications using non-rooted smartphones and small LEDs. With these constraints, our implementation achieves a throughput of 30 bits/second. While limited, this is enough for a feed-back channel coming to support the required redundancy mechanisms. Some of these redundancy mechanisms are based on random linear coding, never tested previously in VLC.
Therefore, we design and implement, for the first time in the literature, a pseudo random linear coding scheme especially fitted for line-of-sight LED-to-camera conditions. Experimental evaluation highlights that this type of approach increases the goodput up to twice compared to classical retransmission strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we compare the energy consumption of LightIoT with the one of a BLE module with similar activity. Our results show that using the LED for communication purposes reduces the energy consumption under a normal usage behavior.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2018 12:06:42 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/jekyll/update/2018/10/04/phd-defense/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/jekyll/update/2018/10/04/phd-defense/</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>2nd Summer School on Security &amp; Correctness in the IoT</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexisduque.me/public/secweek.png&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From September 3 to 7, I attended for the second time the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.securityweek.at/school/&quot;&gt;Summer School on Security &amp;amp; Correctness in the Internet of Things 2018&lt;/a&gt; organized by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iaik.tugraz.at/content/about_iaik/&quot;&gt;IAIK&lt;/a&gt;, in Graz, Austria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, the school was collocated with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.securityweek.at&quot;&gt;IoT Security Week&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top level speakers in the field of security gave presentations about software/hardware attacks and countermeasures: binary exploitation, code reuses/injection, hardware side channels, cache covert channels, formal analysis, lightweight cryptography (LWC), etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://alexisduque.me/public/tugraz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;St Martin&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 18:44:34 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2018/09/15/spring-shool/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2018/09/15/spring-shool/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SSTIC Part 2</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This post is the second part of my notes I took during the SSTIC this year. The first part is available here: &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/13/sstic-part-1/&quot;&gt;SSTIC 2018 Part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rump--nordic-made-easy&quot;&gt;RUMP : Nordic made easy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;salma-el-mohib&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salma El Mohib&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaker from Digital Security presents 3 python scripts for nRF firmware analysis.
Problem: How to reverse a nRF firmware with IDA? How to map it in IDA?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the nRF soft device use SVCALLS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;nrfparse.py&lt;/code&gt;: build the knowledge database from all the Nordic SDK and softdevice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;nrfident.py&lt;/code&gt;: nRF device identification + SDK and Soft Device version to get the memory mapping&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;nrfreverse.py&lt;/code&gt;: used after IDA configuration and firmware disassembly. It parses the assembly code to find SVC opcodes. It selects the appropriate functions prototypes and outputs them in the python output window of IDA pro.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool is available on Github: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/DigitalSecurity/nrf5x-tools&quot;&gt;nrf5x-tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rump-arm_now&quot;&gt;RUMP: ARM_Now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;sanson-chaignon&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sanson Chaignon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ARM_Now is a qemu powered tool that allows instant setup of virtual machines on arm CPU, mips, powerpc, nios2, x86 and more, for reverse, exploit, fuzzing and programming purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ARM_Now is available on Github: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nongiach/arm_now&quot;&gt;arm_now&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;audit-de-sécurité-dun-environnement-docker&quot;&gt;Audit de sécurité d’un environnement Docker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;julien-raeis-matthieu-buffet-anssi&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Julien Raeis, Matthieu Buffet (ANSSI)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker is a lightweight virtualization tool for packaging applications and automating the dev/deployment cycle.
Each application block is a container.
Each container has all the files it depends on.
Docker works under windows &amp;amp; Linux.
For a developer, docker images are black boxes in which the application runs. They often do not master the security of their software execution environment.
On the security side, this presentation will focus on the part that makes the Docker images turn and how to harden the host environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windows Docker containers are based on &lt;code&gt;JOBS&lt;/code&gt; kernel objects that provide a &lt;code&gt;CGROUP&lt;/code&gt; equivalent on Linux.
We can look at the container tree using &lt;code&gt;winobj&lt;/code&gt;.
Each container is in a silo, and in these silos, we discover the isolation mechanism for the symbolic links to be executed in a separate context.
On the filesystem side, the NTFS driver has been patched to handle the isolation.
If it is available, Docker uses Hyper-V to isolate the container and benefits from the Hyper-V isolation mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the audit of a Docker environment, we can control the network interfaces, the permissions on the docker group, mutual authentication by certificates, etc …
If we do not do it, we expose ourselves to an escalation of privileges via Docker.
To avoid denials of service, we often limit the consumption of resources via &lt;code&gt;ulimit&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Namespaces should be reviewed, especially those that allow to make IPC, to do &lt;code&gt;ptrace&lt;/code&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To facilitate the auditing of namespaces, speakers have developed a tool to generate a graph according to which namespace can access which process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Process capabilities can be reduced using the tool &lt;code&gt;pscap&lt;/code&gt;.
Then we can use the docker commands to reduce these capabilities.
When the container has access to real-world resources on the Host, it must be ensured that these resources do not allow elevation of privilege to the Host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Windows Server Containers&lt;/em&gt; are not secure and do not isolate the executed code of the Host. We must therefore favor &lt;em&gt;Hyper-V Containers&lt;/em&gt;, rather than &lt;em&gt;Windows Server Container&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Linux, a &lt;code&gt;seccomp&lt;/code&gt; filter is compiled, so if we must decompile it if we want to audit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers worked on a formal Prolog verifier that takes a &lt;code&gt;seccomp&lt;/code&gt; filter as input and evaluates whether or not specific actions can be performed with this filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve the containers isolation, it is possible to use &lt;em&gt;Orchestrators&lt;/em&gt; based on virtualization, &lt;em&gt;KAtacontainers&lt;/em&gt; that offer an equivalent of &lt;em&gt;Hyper-V Containers&lt;/em&gt; under windows, &lt;em&gt;gVisor&lt;/em&gt; which is a userland kernel made by Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sstic.org/2018/presentation/audit_de_securite_docker/&quot;&gt;Link to the presentaiton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hardening-a-java-card-virtual-machine-implementation-with-the-mpu&quot;&gt;Hardening a Java Card Virtual Machine Implementation with the MPU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;guillaume-bouffard-léo-gaspard&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guillaume Bouffard, Léo Gaspard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker will introduce how to make a JavaCard JVM hardened using the features of a CPU.
To obtain a trusted root, you need a secure and robust component in which you can store a cryptographic secret that will cryptographically sign and verify the integrity of some parts (or all) of the trusted system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JavaCard technology is based on the JVM that runs on a smart card. There is no open-source implementation, but the majority of JavaCard platforms are evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The JVM is often independent of the secure component on which it operates, and the confinement is done at the application level, which at a cost in performance. As a result, the speakers decided to work on this JVM to use the hardware mechanisms of the smart card.
The Memory Protection Unit is configured in privileged mode and allows setting the read/write/execution restrictions. But these configurations are limited to 8 memory regions, roughly 8 pages of MMU on a conventional CPU. One region can be included in another to refine the insulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sstic.org/2018/presentation/hardening_a_java_card_virtual_machine_implementation_with_the_mpu/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dans-les-coulisses-de-léquipe-sécurité-debian&quot;&gt;Dans les coulisses de l’équipe sécurité Debian&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;yves-alexis-perez&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yves-Alexis Perez&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker is a volunteer with the Debian security team.
He will introduce his role in the team and how Debian manages the vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 10 peoples, 5 active, all are volunteers.
Some other guys help: package maintainers, researchers, project maintainers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team job is to manage the distribution security on stable version (Stretch and Jessy).
They prepare packages security updates and write security-announce.
They coordinate with the other teams: developers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Debian security team also contributes to hardening the Debian ecosystem.
However, they do not work on the platform security (Debian account and keys management, CI, Debian LTS, etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They admin the security tracker website that reports the current distribution security state and publish CVE list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security-tracker is a public git repo. They have private repositories, for instance for threats under embargo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also monitor external mailing lists, and their mail address about vulnerability reports.
To help them in this task, they have the External-check tool that is a script that grabs the CVE and adds them to a list. The list is curated by the team;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the vulnerability is identified&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the CVE is assigned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a fix is identified&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the patch is applied&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the package is built locally&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the package is uploaded to security-master&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the package is built by the build bots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the package is released to the security mirror&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;security-announce mail is sent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different kind of vulnerabilities: public, private and complexes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, embargo delay the patch and not developed by many people&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the speaker introduces some example of vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KRACK&lt;/strong&gt;
In August, the CERT contact Debian and share all the details, the draft of the paper, and proofs of concept. In October, wpa_supplicant maintainers contact Debian with their current work and patch proposals.
To conclude, during the embargo, Debian can learn about the vulnerabilities and check that wpa_supplicant patches are working. At the end of the embargo in November, Debian published the update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meltdown&lt;/strong&gt;: very painful for Debian because it was aware of the vulnerability during the embargo period. Debian got the info about Meltdown the same day as the public. So they can’t get prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sstic.org/2018/presentation/debian-security-team/&quot;&gt;Link to the presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-practical-guide-to-differential-power-analysis-of-usim-cards&quot;&gt;A Practical Guide to Differential Power Analysis of USIM Cards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;adrian-thillard-christophe-devine-manuel-san-pedro-anssi&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adrian Thillard, Christophe Devine, Manuel San Pedro (ANSSI)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker begins introducing Milenage, an algorithm used to derivate the credentials in SIM cards.
Thanks to Milenage, the phone can authenticate itself on the operator network.
If an attacker can get secrets from the SIM card, the impact on privacy is huge for the user.
To do this, we can perform a power consumption variations analysis using an oscilloscope, also known as DPA.
This allows an attacker to identify the execution steps of the algorithm.
  from traces of references that are not always very clean because the clock of the card is not super precise.
We must then re-align the peaks in order to have a proper basis of comparison. On the assumption that the data affects consumption.
It requires about 4000 of traces to validate the hypothesis using a 400€ oscilloscope and python scripts. The number of traces required can be reduced using better equipment (e.g a 15000€ oscilloscope).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sstic.org/2018/presentation/a_practical_guide_to_differential_power_analysis_of_usim_cards/&quot;&gt;Link to the presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hacl-une-bibliothèque-de-cryptographie-formellement-vérifiée-dans-firefox&quot;&gt;HACL* une bibliothèque de cryptographie formellement vérifiée dans Firefox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;benjamin-beurdouche-jean-karim-zinzindohoue&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benjamin Beurdouche, Jean Karim Zinzindohoue&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speaker was a member of the INRIA PROCECO team.
He will introduce HACL*, a formally verified crypto library.
Writing crypto is not really easy.
As example, we can have a look at the OpenSSL CVE list: side channel attack, buffer overflow…
It is also true for NaCl (salt) which is a modern primitive cryptographic library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to improve the situation. How can the community help? Using formal methods.
Which approach to choose. 3 axes already exit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using assembly: best performances, no compiler (no bug, no fault introduced), best control on a side channel, ut - specific to the platform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using C: portable, good performance, but introduce a compiler&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;using a high-level programming language: easy, but slow,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus they propose HACL (hacl-star) : a library with a small size, but complete, autonomous, written in F&lt;em&gt;, C code generated from F&lt;/em&gt; code, C code is published&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;F* is a verification oriented language close to OCaml for proof automation.
How to produce C code from F&lt;em&gt;?
F&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; Low* with F* compiler.
Then KreMLin: Low* -&amp;gt; C (correction proof)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is proved: memory safety, execution independency
Safety memory thanks to F*. IF it compiles, the code is safe from the memory point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to prove the code is correct?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HACL* is faster than C implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sstic.org/2018/presentation/hacl_cryptographie_formellement_verifiee_dans_firefox/&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2018 20:03:48 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://alexisduque.me/2018/06/15/sstic-part-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://alexisduque.me/2018/06/15/sstic-part-2/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
